Okay, so maybe you got a little lost in
the hairiness of the code in the last
problem and that is totally
understandable. I want to show you a
tool that will help you with that and
also help you find errors in your code
as you move on. Um, so this what I'm
about to show you is the Firefox
debugger. Um, what that debugger does is
it allows you to go through your code
line by line by line. So all I have done
is I've opened in live server into my
Firefox. Um, this is my file. If I
reload the page,
um, then I get the prompt letter grade
for class one. We'll say A, A, A, and A,
and then it gives us our GPA. So,
exactly where we were in the last video.
Um, so all I'm going to do now is I want
to open the debugger console. If you are
on a Mac, you'll hit commandoption I. If
you're on a Windows, you'll hit control
shift I. So, I'm going to say control
shift I. And it pops up this tool. What
we're going to do is we're going to
click on this debugger tab. So, it may
have opened to the console tab, the
network tab. We're going to go to the
debugger tab,
and you should see a file that looks
quite familiar. In fact, you'll
recognize your code right here. So, what
I'm going to show you is you can put a
break point. So, what you're going to do
is you're going to bring your mouse over
these lines and everywhere that the line
has a different color, like a filledin
white, or it might be a different color
scheme on your computer, um, is where
you can put a breakpoint. What a
breakpoint does is it stops the code and
says, "Hang on, pause. I want to take
charge of how the execution goes from
here on out." So, I'm going to put one
on line 16. So, in order for these to
work, you got to start your script. The
way we start this script is we reload
the page. So, we're going to reload the
page, and it's going to pause, and we're
going to create a counter variable. So,
it says the highlighted portion is what
is going to run next. So, you'll notice
the little blue arrow is pointing at
this zero. In other words, if we look
over here, we can see the counter is
uninitialized, meaning it doesn't have
any values. This is under scopes under
block says counter is uninitialized.
If we hit if we come over here, there's
two buttons. There's the step into and
the step over. We're going to choose
step into. Um, in a later video I'll
explain in a couple weeks I'll explain
what the step into function does, but
we'll say step into and it will step in.
And now it's run that step. So where it
was highlighted over here and counter
was undefined, now counter has been set
to zero, which is exactly what we'd
expect if we had a statement that said
let counter equal zero, we'd assume that
running that line of code would make
counter zero. Now it's highlighting the
next portion. It's going to see if 0 is
less than four. 0 is less than four. So,
it's going to run this loop. So, we'll
hit that step into button or F11.
And now, it's about to run this next
line of code. If we hover over letter
grade, it's not defined yet. And if we
look over here, it's uninitialized.
But if we hit the next button, it runs
our prompt. And it's going to run a
prompt that says, what is the letter
grade for class counter is zero plus
one. So, we should see what is the your
letter grade for class one. If we hit
the next button, says, "What is your
letter grade for class one?" I'm going
to put a B+ here and hit okay. So now it
says that letter grade is B+. It was
uninitialized, but now it's a B+. GPA is
still uninitialized, but when we hit the
next button, it's going to run this line
of code. So let's hit that next button.
And boom, GPA is now zero. We can see
GPA is zero and letter grade is B+. Now
it starts our if statement. It's going
to see if letter grade is equal to A. B+
is not equal to A. So we should expect
it to skip straight to line 24 and run
that check next. So we'll hit the next
button and it jumps to line 24. And it
says letter grade B+ equals A minus. It
does not. So we should expect it to jump
to line 27. We hit next and sure enough
it jumps to line 27. Now we're going to
see if letter grade equals B+. So B+
equals B+. It does. So now we're going
to expect it to go to line 28 and run
that letter grade. So we hit next. Now
we're on line 28. Right now GPA is still
zero because we set it up above. Um
right here we set it to zero. But here
we're about to set it to 3.3. So we see
it's zero right now. Um once we hit the
next button, we finished evaluating this
if statement. We don't need to check any
of the others cuz we already know that
B+ is B+. So, we're going to skip down
to line 57. So, we'll hit next. It skips
to line 57. If we hover over GPA, we can
see it's 3.3. If we hover over total
GPA, right now it's zero because we
haven't entered any classes.
So, now we're going to store total GPA.
Um, total GPA is going to be zero plus
whatever is in GPA, 3.3. So, if we hit
next and we hover over total GPA, it's
3.3. We also happen to hit the end of
the loop. So it jumped right back up to
the top. Now you'll notice the
highlighter is over this counter plus+.
So if counter is zero and plus+
increments it then we should expect
counter to change to one. So we'll hit
that next statement. And now counter is
one. And now we're going to see if one
is less than four. One is less than
four. So we should expect this loop to
start again. We'll drop into the loop.
Um letter grade is uninitialized. GPA
uninitialized.
We're going to say, "What is your grade
for class 2?" Because we knew that
counter was one. 1 plus 1 is two. We'll
put an A. So, you can see that in
action. Um, so now our letter grade is
an A. And our GPA is still
uninitialized, but if we hit next, now
our GPA is set to zero and our letter
grade is set to A. If letter grade is A,
then we expect line 22 to run. If we
hover over letter grade, it is in fact
A. So, we'll drop down and we'll run 4.0
and drop to the end. At this point,
we've now run our loop two times. We're
about to increment the GPA. It's going
to go from 3.3 to 3.3 + 4. So, that
should be like 7.3. Um,
but we know that our loop is working. So
when you're debugging your code and
you've established that a block of code
is working and maybe it runs multiple
times, if you are done debugging it, you
can remove the break point and come to
the next block of code you want to
analyze. In my case, I want to just
start it um right here because I want to
make sure that my math works, that I
will be getting the right GPA. So then
once you've done that, you can hit this
resume button and that'll run the code
normally. So it's going to say, what is
your letter grade for class 3? Um, we're
going to put a C minus and hit okay. And
you'll notice it didn't pause and it
went immediately to class 4. So, what is
your letter grade for class 4? We'll
give ourselves another A.
And now it pauses. Total GPA is now 13
because that's the GPA you got in each
class. And now we're averaging it to get
your actual GPA. Uh, because that's
grade point average. Um, so in order to
get that, we have to divide it by the
number of classes that you took, which
is four. So, we'll take 13 and we'll
divide it by four. And if we hit the
next button, now our total GPA is 3.25.
So, we know that math works now. Um, and
now we've gotten to our if statement.
In future programs that you're writing,
you may want to test some of your if
statements. And right now, our GPA is
3.25. And while it's relatively easy to
figure out what letter grades you need
to get to figure out each of these
conditions, sometimes it's going to be a
little harder. So, what I'm going to
show you how to do is called forcing a
condition. Let's say we actually really
wanted to check that this first if
statement is working. Our total GPA
needs to be greater than or equal to
3.3. Let's say we really want to test if
that equal part works. Like, what if we
have exactly 3.3? Which of these
conditions is it going to evaluate?
Well, problematically, our GPA is 3.25
um after all of those calculations. But
because we have the power of the
debugger and we've paused the code, it
actually hasn't run line 63 yet. So,
what we can do is we can come to our
console and we can say total GPA
equals and then we can set it to what we
want. So, we wanted to see if it what
happens when total GPA is 3.3. So we'll
say total GPA equals 3.3 and we'll hit
enter. Now when we come back to our
debugger and we hover over it, total GPA
is 3.3. Now when it evaluates this line,
even though we our entire calculation
before came out to 3.25, we said throw
that out the window, set it to 3.3. So
now that it's set to 3.3, we can see if
3.3 is greater than or equal to 3.3,
then run line 64.
We'll hit next. And because we've now
forced the condition to take place, we
can now make sure that this part of our
if statement works. So now we're going
to alert um that your GPA is 3.3. Great
job. And then continue on with the rest
of that alert. So we'll hit the next
button. It says your GPA is 3.3. And
we've successfully forced the condition.
So now we'll hit okay. So that's really
helpful for when you're wanting to test
why something isn't working. you're
like, maybe I need to test a very unique
input and I don't want to figure out how
to get that input by the time we get
halfway down the program. And so you can
wait until you get halfway down the
program and then change the value and
then you can test your code accordingly.
All right. So when you um hit next,
it'll drop all the way to the bottom of
the script tag and you'll see all those
comments that we had in there. Um, now
if you were running this uh without
lifeserver then your code would have
just ended because you're running it
with liveserver. Liveserver puts some
some of their own javascript in here and
that's this stuff and it's complicated
and don't look at it. You don't need to.
I mean you can if you want to. Um, but
you are good to go from this point. So
you can just hit continue and then
you'll see your HTML page like you
normally would. And that is how you use
the Firefox debugger.